<b>Introduction to Digital Speech Processing
by Lawrence R. Rabiner and Ronald W. Schafer

<a>Abstract
Since even before the time of Alexander Graham Bell¡¦s revolutionary invention, engineers and scientists have studied the phenomenon of speech communication with an eye on creating more efficient and effective systems of human-to-human and human-to-machine communication.

Starting in the 1960s, digital signal processing (DSP), assumed a central role in speech studies, and today DSP is the key to realizing the fruits of the knowledge that has been gained through decades of research.

Concomitant advances in integrated circuit technology and computer architecture have aligned to create a technological environment with virtually limitless opportunities for innovation in speech communication applications.

In this text, we highlight the central role of DSP techniques in modern speech communication research and applications.

We present a comprehensive overview of digital speech processing that ranges from the basic nature of the speech signal, through a variety of methods of representing speech in digital form, to applications in voice communication and automatic synthesis and recognition of speech.

The breadth of this subject does not allow us to discuss any aspect of speech processing to great depth; hence our goal is to provide a useful introduction to the wide range of important concepts that comprise the field of digital speech processing.

A more comprehensive treatment will appear in the forthcoming book, Theory and Application of Digital Speech Processing [101].
</a>
<c>	1.	Introduction
1.1	The Speech Chain
1.2	Applications of Digital Speech Processing
</c>
<c>	2.	The Speech Signal
2.1	Phonetic Representation of Speech
2.2	Models for Speech Production
</c>
<c>	3.	Hearing and Auditory Perception
3.1	The Human Ear
3.2	Perception of Loudness
3.3	Critical Bands
3.4	Pitch Perception
3.5	Auditory Masking
3.6	Complete Model of Auditory Processing
</c>
<c>	4.	Short-Time Analysis of Speech
4.1	Short-time energy and Zero-Crossing rate
4.2	Short-time Autocorrelation Function (STACF)
4.3	Short-time Fourier Transform (STFT)
4.4	Sampling the STFT in Time and Frequency
4.5	The Speech Spectrogram
</c>
<c>	5.	Homomorphic Speech Analysis
5.1	Cepstrum 
5.2	Short-time Cepstrum
5.3	Computation of Cepstrum
5.4	Hormomorphic Filtering of Speech
5.5	Application to Pitch Detection and Pattern Recognition
</c>
<c>	6.	Linear Predictive Analysis
6.1	Linear Prediction and the Speech Model
6.2	Computing the Linear Prediction Coefficients (LPC)
6.2.1	The Levinson-Durbin Recursion
6.3	LPC Spectrum
6.4	Equivalent Representations
</c>
<c>	7.	Digital Speech Coding
7.1	Sampling and Quantization of Speech
7.2	Digital Speech Coding
7.3	Closed-Loop Coders
7.4	Open-Loop Coders
7.5	Frequency-Domain Coders
7.6	Evaluation of Coders
</c>
<c>	8.	Text-to-Speech Synthesis Methods (TTS)
8.1	Text Analysis
8.2	Evolution of Speech Synthesis Systems
8.3	Unit Selection Methods
8.4	TTS Applications
</c>
<c>	9.	Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR)
9.1	The Problem of Automatic Speech Recognition
9.2	Building a Speech Recognition System
9.3	The Decision Process in ASR
9.4	Representative Recognition Performance
9.5	Challenges in ASR Technology
</c>
</b>
